<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss xmlns:itunes="http://www.itunes.com/dtds/podcast-1.0.dtd" version="2.0"><channel><title>Anonymous Narration Feed</title><link>https://surly-16.github.io/js-audio-feed/</link><description>Strategic narrated content on AI, banking, and innovation</description><language>en-au</language><itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit><itunes:image href="https://github.com/surly-16/js-audio-feed/blob/main/Cover.png?raw=true" /><image><url>https://github.com/surly-16/js-audio-feed/blob/main/Cover.png?raw=true</url><title>Anonymous Narration Feed</title><link>https://surly-16.github.io/js-audio-feed/</link></image><item><title>Reating Self Documenting Agent Systems For Regulatory Compliance</title><enclosure url="https://github.com/surly-16/js-audio-feed/raw/refs/heads/main/Media//reating_self_documenting_agent_systems_for_regulatory_compliance.mp3" length="827565" type="audio/mpeg" /><guid>reating_self_documenting_agent_systems_for_regulatory_compliance</guid><pubDate>Sat, 14 Jun 2025 23:50:21 +1000</pubDate><description>Narrated episode: Reating Self Documenting Agent Systems For Regulatory Compliance

So, here's something I've been thinking about lately.  Last week, I was in a meeting with our compliance team, and they mentioned something that really stuck with me. They said, "We spend more time documenting what our systems did than actually improving them."  And you know what? They're absolutely right.

[PAUSE]

Let me paint you a picture of where we are today.  Every time we deploy an automated process—whether it's for credit decisioning, transaction monitoring, or customer service routing—we create what I call a &amp;quot;documentation debt.&amp;quot;  Teams scramble to write up how the system works, what decisions it made, and why.  But here's the kicker: by the time that documentation is complete, the system has already evolved.



Now, imagine if our agent systems could document themselves.  Not just logging what they did, but explaining why they did it, in language that both our technical teams and our regulators can understand.  That's what we're going to explore today.

[PAUSE]

Let's start with the core concept.  A self-documenting agent system is essentially an AI-powered process that maintains its own audit trail, but goes beyond traditional logging.  It captures decision rationale, contextual factors, and even uncertainty levels—all in real-time.



Think of it like this:  Instead of a black box that spits out decisions, you have a glass box that shows you exactly how it arrived at each conclusion.  And the best part? It writes this explanation as it works, not as an afterthought.

[PAUSE]

From a technical perspective, we're talking about three key components.  First, structured decision logging using frameworks like LangChain or similar tools.  Every step in the agent's reasoning chain gets captured with metadata—timestamps, confidence scores, data sources used.



Second, natural language generation for explanations.  The system doesn't just log &amp;quot;Decision: Approve loan&amp;quot;—it writes, &amp;quot;Approved loan application based on debt-to-income ratio of 35%, stable employment history of 5 years, and credit score of 720.&amp;quot;



Third, and this is crucial—version control for prompts and models.  Every change to how the system thinks gets tracked, tagged, and linked to specific outcomes.  It's like Git for AI decision-making.

[PAUSE]

Now, let me share some concrete use cases from our banking context.  Take our risk assessment workflows.  Currently, when a transaction gets flagged, someone has to dig through logs, reconstruct the logic, and write up why it was flagged.  With self-documenting agents, the system would generate a compliance-ready report instantly: &amp;quot;Transaction flagged due to unusual pattern: 300% increase from typical spending, merchant category mismatch, and geographic anomaly.&amp;quot;



Or consider customer complaint handling.  When our AI routes a complaint to a specific team, it could automatically document: &amp;quot;Routed to mortgage team based on keyword analysis (refinance, rate, terms), sentiment score of -0.7 indicating high frustration, and customer profile showing active home loan.&amp;quot;

[PAUSE]

But here's where it gets really interesting for governance and decision-making.  These self-documenting systems create what I call &amp;quot;decision lineage&amp;quot;—a complete trace from input to output that satisfies regulatory requirements without manual intervention.



For APRA reporting, for instance, we could automatically generate documentation showing how our credit models make decisions, complete with feature importance scores and counterfactual explanations.  &amp;quot;If the applicant's income was $10,000 higher, the decision would have changed to approved.&amp;quot;



This isn't just about compliance—it's about trust.  When our risk managers can see exactly why a system made a decision, they can confidently defend it to regulators, auditors, and customers.

[PAUSE]

Now, let's talk about what's emerging in this space.  We're seeing new patterns like &amp;quot;explanation-first design,&amp;quot; where you actually write the explanation template before building the decision logic.  It forces you to think about interpretability from day one.



There's also growing interest in what I call &amp;quot;regulatory prompt engineering&amp;quot;—designing prompts that naturally produce outputs aligned with compliance requirements.  Instead of retrofitting documentation, you build it into the agent's core behavior.



And here's something fascinating:  Some teams are experimenting with dual-agent architectures, where one agent makes decisions and another agent audits and documents those decisions in real-time.  It's like having a built-in compliance officer for every automated process.

[PAUSE]

So, what does this mean for us practically?  Here are your actionable takeaways.



First, start small.  Pick one process—maybe transaction monitoring or customer categorization—and retrofit it with self-documentation capabilities.  Use structured outputs, capture decision factors, and generate plain-English explanations.



Second, establish documentation standards now.  What needs to be captured? How should explanations be formatted? What level of detail do different stakeholders need?  Create templates that your agents can fill in.



Third, invest in prompt versioning and testing infrastructure.  Every prompt change should be traceable to specific outcomes and documentation quality metrics.



Fourth, engage your compliance and risk teams early.  Show them prototypes, get their input on explanation quality, and iterate based on their needs.  They're not just stakeholders—they're co-designers of these systems.

[PAUSE]

As we wrap up, I want you to think about this:  In five years, will we still be manually documenting what our AI systems do?  Or will we have systems that explain themselves better than we ever could?



The technology is here. The regulatory need is clear.  The question is: How quickly can we move from reactive documentation to proactive, self-explaining systems?



Think about your own workflows.  Where are you spending time explaining what automated systems did?  Those are your opportunities.  Those are where self-documenting agents can transform not just efficiency, but trust and transparency in everything we do.



The future of compliance isn't more documentation—it's smarter documentation.  And that future starts with the systems we build today.</description><link>https://github.com/surly-16/js-audio-feed/raw/refs/heads/main/Media//reating_self_documenting_agent_systems_for_regulatory_compliance.txt</link></item><item><title>Designing Adaptive Prompt Libraries For Cross Domain Banking Applications</title><enclosure url="https://github.com/surly-16/js-audio-feed/raw/refs/heads/main/Media//designing_adaptive_prompt_libraries_for_cross_domain_banking_applications.mp3" length="4541421" type="audio/mpeg" /><guid>designing_adaptive_prompt_libraries_for_cross_domain_banking_applications</guid><pubDate>Sat, 14 Jun 2025 23:23:05 +1000</pubDate><description>Narrated episode: Designing Adaptive Prompt Libraries For Cross Domain Banking Applications</description><link>https://github.com/surly-16/js-audio-feed/raw/refs/heads/main/Media//designing_adaptive_prompt_libraries_for_cross_domain_banking_applications.txt</link></item><item><title>Creating Reusable Agent Templates For Cross Functional Banking Workflow</title><enclosure url="https://github.com/surly-16/js-audio-feed/raw/refs/heads/main/Media//creating_reusable_agent_templates_for_cross_functional_banking_workflow.mp3" length="6503277" type="audio/mpeg" /><guid>creating_reusable_agent_templates_for_cross_functional_banking_workflow</guid><pubDate>Sat, 14 Jun 2025 22:52:29 +1000</pubDate><description>Narrated episode: Creating Reusable Agent Templates For Cross Functional Banking Workflow</description><link>https://github.com/surly-16/js-audio-feed/raw/refs/heads/main/Media//creating_reusable_agent_templates_for_cross_functional_banking_workflow.txt</link></item><item><title>Creating Reusable Agent Templates For Cross Functional Banking Workflows</title><enclosure url="https://github.com/surly-16/js-audio-feed/raw/refs/heads/main/Media//creating_reusable_agent_templates_for_cross_functional_banking_workflows.mp3" length="2679021" type="audio/mpeg" /><guid>creating_reusable_agent_templates_for_cross_functional_banking_workflows</guid><pubDate>Sat, 14 Jun 2025 21:48:46 +1000</pubDate><description>Narrated episode: Creating Reusable Agent Templates For Cross Functional Banking Workflows</description><link>https://github.com/surly-16/js-audio-feed/raw/refs/heads/main/Media//creating_reusable_agent_templates_for_cross_functional_banking_workflows.txt</link></item><item><title>Designing Optimal Agent Architectures For Scalable Ai Workflows</title><enclosure url="https://github.com/surly-16/js-audio-feed/raw/refs/heads/main/Media//designing_optimal_agent_architectures_for_scalable_ai_workflows.mp3" length="2987949" type="audio/mpeg" /><guid>designing_optimal_agent_architectures_for_scalable_ai_workflows</guid><pubDate>Sat, 14 Jun 2025 21:29:40 +1000</pubDate><description>Narrated episode: Designing Optimal Agent Architectures For Scalable Ai Workflows</description><link>https://github.com/surly-16/js-audio-feed/raw/refs/heads/main/Media//designing_optimal_agent_architectures_for_scalable_ai_workflows.txt</link></item><item><title>Ssml Output</title><enclosure url="https://github.com/surly-16/js-audio-feed/raw/refs/heads/main/Media//ssml_output.mp3" length="1006317" type="audio/mpeg" /><guid>ssml_output</guid><pubDate>Sat, 14 Jun 2025 21:10:35 +1000</pubDate><description>Narrated episode: Ssml Output</description><link>https://github.com/surly-16/js-audio-feed/raw/refs/heads/main/Media//ssml_output.txt</link></item></channel></rss>