<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss xmlns:itunes="http://www.itunes.com/dtds/podcast-1.0.dtd" version="2.0"><channel><title>Anonymous Narration Feed</title><link>https://surly-16.github.io/js-audio-feed/</link><description>Strategic narrated content on AI, banking, and innovation</description><language>en-au</language><itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit><itunes:image href="https://github.com/surly-16/js-audio-feed/blob/main/Cover.png?raw=true" /><image><url>https://github.com/surly-16/js-audio-feed/blob/main/Cover.png?raw=true</url><title>Anonymous Narration Feed</title><link>https://surly-16.github.io/js-audio-feed/</link></image><item><title>Creating Reusable Agent Templates For Cross Functional Banking Workflows</title><enclosure url="https://github.com/surly-16/js-audio-feed/raw/refs/heads/main/Media//creating_reusable_agent_templates_for_cross_functional_banking_workflows.mp3" length="2679021" type="audio/mpeg" /><guid>creating_reusable_agent_templates_for_cross_functional_banking_workflows</guid><pubDate>Sat, 14 Jun 2025 21:48:46 +1000</pubDate><description>Narrated episode: Creating Reusable Agent Templates For Cross Functional Banking Workflows

So here's something I've been thinking about lately.  We've all seen how AI agents are transforming banking operations, but there's a pattern emerging that's worth discussing. What if we could create agent templates that work across multiple teams, from risk assessment to customer service, without rebuilding from scratch each time?

[PAUSE]

Let me paint you a picture of where we are today.  Most of our teams are building their own AI workflows in isolation. Risk Management has their credit assessment agents. Customer Experience has their query resolution bots. Compliance has their document review systems.  Each one is powerful, but they're all speaking different languages and following different patterns.

The cost of this fragmentation isn't just technical debt—it's missed opportunities for scale and consistency.

[PAUSE]

So what are reusable agent templates, really? Think of them as blueprints for intelligent workflows that can be configured for different contexts.  At their core, they share three components: a standardized input interface, a flexible reasoning engine, and an output formatter that speaks the language of each team.

Here's the technical foundation.  We're talking about Python-based frameworks that abstract the common patterns—things like data validation, prompt engineering, error handling, and audit logging. The magic happens when you parameterize the domain-specific elements. Instead of hardcoding risk thresholds or customer intent categories, you inject them as configuration.

[PAUSE]

Let me share a concrete example from our recent work.  We built a template for what we call a "Decision Analysis Agent." The same base template now powers three different workflows.

First, in Risk Management, it analyzes loan applications by evaluating financial indicators against dynamic risk policies.  Second, in Customer Service, it determines the best resolution path for complex queries by matching intent patterns.  Third, in Product Development, it assesses feature requests against strategic priorities and technical constraints.

Same template. Three completely different business outcomes.

[PAUSE]

The banking context makes this especially powerful.  We operate in an environment where every decision needs an audit trail, every process needs governance approval, and every output could be scrutinized by regulators.  When you build these requirements into the template layer, you get compliance by default, not by afterthought.

Consider our document processing template.  Whether it's analyzing mortgage applications, reviewing compliance documents, or extracting insights from market reports, the core workflow remains consistent: ingest, validate, extract, enrich, and route. The template handles the orchestration while team-specific plugins handle the domain logic.

[PAUSE]

Now, this approach fundamentally changes how we think about governance and decision-making.  Instead of approving individual agent implementations, we can establish governance at the template level. Risk committees review the base patterns once, then teams can deploy variations within approved guardrails.

This also transforms our change management process.  When regulatory requirements shift—and they always do—we update the template, and every workflow built on it inherits the changes. No more hunting through dozens of implementations to ensure compliance.

[PAUSE]

Let me share what's emerging on the horizon.  We're seeing templates evolve into what I call "composite agents"—templates that orchestrate other templates. Imagine a customer onboarding workflow that seamlessly combines identity verification, risk assessment, and product recommendation agents.

The next frontier is dynamic template selection.  Instead of humans choosing which template to use, we're building meta-agents that analyze the task and automatically select and configure the right template. It's like having an AI architect that designs the optimal workflow in real-time.

[PAUSE]

So what can you do with this tomorrow?  Start by identifying the patterns in your current workflows. Look for the repetitive structures hiding beneath the domain-specific details. Every team has them.

Build your first template around a simple, well-understood process.  Maybe it's document classification or data validation. Keep it focused, but design for extensibility from day one. Remember, the goal isn't to solve every problem—it's to create a foundation others can build upon.

Most importantly, involve your governance and risk partners early.  Show them how templates can enhance oversight, not circumvent it. When they see standardized audit trails and consistent control points, they become your biggest advocates.

[PAUSE]

Here's what I want you to reflect on.  What if the real value of AI in banking isn't in the individual use cases, but in our ability to scale intelligence systematically?  What if every team could deploy sophisticated agents not in months, but in days, because the hard problems were already solved at the template layer?

That's the future we're building toward. And it starts with recognizing that in enterprise AI, reusability isn't just about efficiency—it's about creating a new operational paradigm.</description><link>https://github.com/surly-16/js-audio-feed/raw/refs/heads/main/Media//creating_reusable_agent_templates_for_cross_functional_banking_workflows.txt</link></item><item><title>Designing Optimal Agent Architectures For Scalable Ai Workflows</title><enclosure url="https://github.com/surly-16/js-audio-feed/raw/refs/heads/main/Media//designing_optimal_agent_architectures_for_scalable_ai_workflows.mp3" length="2987949" type="audio/mpeg" /><guid>designing_optimal_agent_architectures_for_scalable_ai_workflows</guid><pubDate>Sat, 14 Jun 2025 21:29:40 +1000</pubDate><description>Narrated episode: Designing Optimal Agent Architectures For Scalable Ai Workflows</description><link>https://github.com/surly-16/js-audio-feed/raw/refs/heads/main/Media//designing_optimal_agent_architectures_for_scalable_ai_workflows.txt</link></item><item><title>Ssml Output</title><enclosure url="https://github.com/surly-16/js-audio-feed/raw/refs/heads/main/Media//ssml_output.mp3" length="1006317" type="audio/mpeg" /><guid>ssml_output</guid><pubDate>Sat, 14 Jun 2025 21:10:35 +1000</pubDate><description>Narrated episode: Ssml Output</description><link>https://github.com/surly-16/js-audio-feed/raw/refs/heads/main/Media//ssml_output.txt</link></item></channel></rss>