<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<rss xmlns:itunes="http://www.itunes.com/dtds/podcast-1.0.dtd" version="2.0"><channel><title>Governance, Value and Strategy Feed</title><link>https://surly-16.github.io/js-audio-feed/Governance,%20Value%20and%20Strategy/</link><description>Narrated episodes on Governance, Value and Strategy</description><language>en-au</language><itunes:explicit>no</itunes:explicit><itunes:image href="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/surly-16/js-audio-feed/refs/heads/main/Governance,%20Value%20and%20Strategy/Cover.png" /><image><url>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/surly-16/js-audio-feed/refs/heads/main/Governance,%20Value%20and%20Strategy/Cover.png</url><title>Governance, Value and Strategy Feed</title><link>https://surly-16.github.io/js-audio-feed/Governance,%20Value%20and%20Strategy/</link></image><item><title>007 Ai Success Metrics And Kpis For Banking</title><guid>007_ai_success_metrics_and_kpis_for_banking</guid><pubDate>Sun, 15 Jun 2025 04:25:59 +1000</pubDate><enclosure url="https://github.com/surly-16/js-audio-feed/raw/refs/heads/main/Governance,%20Value%20and%20Strategy/media/007_ai_success_metrics_and_kpis_for_banking.mp3" length="5163501" type="audio/mpeg" /><description>Narrated episode: 007 Ai Success Metrics And Kpis For Banking

Right now, your bank is likely tracking AI success through the lens of cost reduction and automation rates. But here's what we're missing—the metrics that actually predict whether your AI initiatives will scale beyond proof of concept and deliver sustainable value in a regulated environment.

I've spent the last eighteen months building AI capabilities across risk, compliance, and operations teams. The difference between projects that thrive and those that get quietly shelved? It's not the technology—it's how we measure success from day one.

Let's start with the foundational metric most banks get wrong: model confidence versus business confidence. Your data scientists are tracking AUC scores and F1 metrics, but your risk committee wants to know if they can trust the system when APRA comes knocking. 

Here's what actually moves the needle. First, regulatory alignment score. Every AI system needs a clear mapping to specific regulatory requirements—CPS 230 for operational resilience, ASIC Report 798 for fairness testing. Track how many regulatory checkpoints your model passes automatically versus requiring manual review. When CBA launched their AI Factory, they built compliance tracking directly into their MLOps pipeline. Models that couldn't demonstrate clear audit trails never made it to production.

Second metric: decision explainability index. Not just "can we explain it" but "can a risk analyst explain it to a regulator in under five minutes." We measure this through structured testing—randomly select model decisions, time how long it takes different stakeholders to understand and document the logic. Anything over five minutes needs redesign. 


Think about your current fraud detection systems. Traditional rules might flag transactions over ten thousand dollars from new devices. ML models consider hundreds of features simultaneously. But if your fraud analyst can't articulate why a specific transaction was blocked, you've created a compliance liability, not an asset.


Third critical measure: operational integration velocity. How quickly can your teams actually adopt and trust AI outputs? We track this through usage analytics—not just logins, but meaningful actions taken based on AI recommendations. Westpac reported forty percent productivity gains in their mortgage processing, but the real insight was their integration metric: time from AI recommendation to human action dropped from hours to minutes over six months.

Here's where Lean Six Sigma thinking transforms AI implementation. Instead of measuring model accuracy in isolation, we measure process capability improvement. Your AI doesn't need to be perfect—it needs to consistently improve your process sigma level. 

Take credit risk assessment. Traditional metrics focus on prediction accuracy. But what matters operationally? Measure the reduction in decision cycle time while maintaining or improving risk-adjusted returns. Track how many decisions move from multiple touchpoints to single-review processes. Monitor the decrease in inconsistent decisions across different assessors.

Fourth metric, often overlooked: knowledge transfer coefficient. As your AI systems learn, are your people learning too? We measure this through competency assessments before and after AI implementation. Teams using AI should become better at their jobs, not just faster. Track how many junior analysts can now handle complex cases previously requiring senior oversight.


Let me share a practical example from our trade surveillance enhancement. Instead of just tracking false positive reduction—which was sixty percent—we measured analyst investigation quality scores. Analysts using AI-prioritized alerts identified twice as many genuine issues in half the time. That's the compound value of human-AI collaboration.


Fifth essential measure: technical debt ratio. Every AI system accumulates technical debt through model drift, changing regulations, and evolving business rules. Track the effort required to maintain model performance versus the value delivered. When maintenance exceeds twenty percent of initial development effort annually, it's time to architect for sustainability, not just performance. 

Now, let's talk about stakeholder-specific KPIs. Your board wants different metrics than your technical teams. For executive reporting, focus on strategic value indicators: market share protection through better risk decisions, regulatory fine avoidance through improved compliance, customer satisfaction improvements through faster processing.

For operational teams, emphasize workload distribution metrics. How many routine decisions has AI absorbed? What percentage of complex cases now get human attention? Track the shift from reactive to proactive work—analysts spending time on investigation rather than data gathering.

Here's a metric that predicts long-term success: voluntary adoption rate. When teams choose to use AI tools without mandates, you've achieved true value delivery. We track this through system analytics—comparing mandatory versus discretionary usage patterns. High-performing AI initiatives show seventy percent plus voluntary adoption within six months.

Sixth crucial indicator: model governance maturity. Beyond having policies, how consistently are they applied? Track the percentage of models with complete lineage documentation, regular performance reviews, and automated bias testing. Grant Thornton's research shows banks with mature model governance see forty percent fewer production issues and significantly reduced regulatory scrutiny. 


Consider this governance hierarchy: Level one—models have basic documentation. Level two—automated performance monitoring with alerts. Level three—continuous fairness testing across protected attributes. Level four—predictive maintenance identifying issues before they impact decisions. Level five—self-healing systems that automatically retrain within approved parameters.


Most banks operate between levels two and three. The investment to reach level four pays off through reduced operational risk and increased regulator confidence.

Seventh metric for sustainable success: cross-functional value creation. AI in banking can't succeed in silos. Measure how many processes span multiple departments with shared KPIs. When risk, compliance, and business teams share success metrics for the same AI system, you've achieved organizational alignment.

Example: Customer onboarding involves identity verification, risk assessment, and regulatory screening. Instead of three separate AI initiatives, create unified metrics—total onboarding time, aggregate risk score accuracy, and composite compliance confidence. This drives collaboration over competition.

Eighth indicator, critical for scale: reusability index. What percentage of your AI components—data pipelines, feature engineering, model architectures—can be leveraged across use cases? High-maturity organizations achieve sixty percent plus reusability. This dramatically reduces time-to-value for new initiatives. 

Let's address the elephant in the room—ROI calculation for AI in regulated environments. Traditional ROI focuses on cost savings and revenue generation. In banking, add risk-adjusted returns and compliance cost avoidance. Every prevented regulatory breach, every avoided operational loss event—these need quantification in your business case.


Here's the framework we use: Direct benefits include processing cost reduction and speed improvements. Indirect benefits capture risk mitigation and compliance enhancement. Strategic benefits encompass market positioning and innovation capability. Weight these equally in your ROI calculations—focusing only on direct benefits undervalues AI's true impact.


Ninth essential metric: model resilience score. How well do your AI systems perform under stress? Track performance degradation under various scenarios—data quality issues, volume spikes, edge cases. Resilient systems maintain acceptable performance when conditions deviate from training parameters. This is especially critical for risk and compliance applications where failure has significant consequences.

Finally, measure cultural transformation indicators. Survey teams on their confidence in AI decisions, their understanding of model limitations, and their ability to override when necessary. The goal isn't blind trust—it's informed collaboration. Track the evolution from skepticism through acceptance to advocacy. 

Implementation guidance for these metrics: Start with a balanced scorecard approach. Technical metrics for model performance, operational metrics for process improvement, strategic metrics for business value, and cultural metrics for adoption success. Weight these based on your organization's AI maturity and strategic priorities.

For teams transitioning from RPA and VBA automation, focus initially on operational metrics. These create clear connections between familiar automation benefits and AI's expanded capabilities. As comfort grows, introduce more sophisticated measures around model governance and strategic value.

Remember, the metrics you choose shape the behavior you get. If you only measure accuracy, teams optimize for accuracy at the expense of explainability. If you only measure speed, quality suffers. Balance is essential.


Here's your call to action: Audit your current AI initiatives against these metrics. Identify the three biggest gaps—likely in explainability, governance maturity, or cross-functional value. Build measurement frameworks for these gaps before your next model deployment. The effort invested in comprehensive measurement pays dividends through faster adoption, reduced risk, and demonstrated value that secures ongoing investment.


The banks winning with AI aren't necessarily those with the most sophisticated models. They're the ones who measure what matters, iterate based on evidence, and align AI success with organizational success. In a regulated environment, that alignment isn't optional—it's the difference between transformation and expensive experimentation.</description></item><item><title>006 Measuring Ai Roi Beyond Cost Savings</title><guid>006_measuring_ai_roi_beyond_cost_savings</guid><pubDate>Sun, 15 Jun 2025 04:25:56 +1000</pubDate><enclosure url="https://github.com/surly-16/js-audio-feed/raw/refs/heads/main/Governance,%20Value%20and%20Strategy/media/006_measuring_ai_roi_beyond_cost_savings.mp3" length="5261805" type="audio/mpeg" /><description>Narrated episode: 006 Measuring Ai Roi Beyond Cost Savings</description></item><item><title>009 Vendor Risk And Third Party Ai Management</title><guid>009_vendor_risk_and_third_party_ai_management</guid><pubDate>Sun, 15 Jun 2025 04:15:03 +1000</pubDate><enclosure url="https://github.com/surly-16/js-audio-feed/raw/refs/heads/main/Governance,%20Value%20and%20Strategy/media/009_vendor_risk_and_third_party_ai_management.mp3" length="5425965" type="audio/mpeg" /><description>Narrated episode: 009 Vendor Risk And Third Party Ai Management</description></item><item><title>005 Quick Wins Vs Strategic Ai Initiatives</title><guid>005_quick_wins_vs_strategic_ai_initiatives</guid><pubDate>Sun, 15 Jun 2025 04:14:27 +1000</pubDate><enclosure url="https://github.com/surly-16/js-audio-feed/raw/refs/heads/main/Governance,%20Value%20and%20Strategy/media/005_quick_wins_vs_strategic_ai_initiatives.mp3" length="6577773" type="audio/mpeg" /><description>Narrated episode: 005 Quick Wins Vs Strategic Ai Initiatives</description></item><item><title>008 Demonstrating Ai Value To Regulators And Stakeholders</title><guid>008_demonstrating_ai_value_to_regulators_and_stakeholders</guid><pubDate>Sun, 15 Jun 2025 04:14:15 +1000</pubDate><enclosure url="https://github.com/surly-16/js-audio-feed/raw/refs/heads/main/Governance,%20Value%20and%20Strategy/media/008_demonstrating_ai_value_to_regulators_and_stakeholders.mp3" length="4573101" type="audio/mpeg" /><description>Narrated episode: 008 Demonstrating Ai Value To Regulators And Stakeholders</description></item><item><title>004 Risk Based Ai Roadmap Development</title><guid>004_risk_based_ai_roadmap_development</guid><pubDate>Sun, 15 Jun 2025 03:36:42 +1000</pubDate><enclosure url="https://github.com/surly-16/js-audio-feed/raw/refs/heads/main/Governance,%20Value%20and%20Strategy/media/004_risk_based_ai_roadmap_development.mp3" length="5001069" type="audio/mpeg" /><description>Narrated episode: 004 Risk Based Ai Roadmap Development</description></item><item><title>002 Ai Governance Gaps And Model Risk Management</title><guid>002_ai_governance_gaps_and_model_risk_management</guid><pubDate>Sun, 15 Jun 2025 03:36:03 +1000</pubDate><enclosure url="https://github.com/surly-16/js-audio-feed/raw/refs/heads/main/Governance,%20Value%20and%20Strategy/media/002_ai_governance_gaps_and_model_risk_management.mp3" length="4841709" type="audio/mpeg" /><description>Narrated episode: 002 Ai Governance Gaps And Model Risk Management</description></item><item><title>003 Building Compliant Ai Governance Frameworks</title><guid>003_building_compliant_ai_governance_frameworks</guid><pubDate>Sun, 15 Jun 2025 03:35:37 +1000</pubDate><enclosure url="https://github.com/surly-16/js-audio-feed/raw/refs/heads/main/Governance,%20Value%20and%20Strategy/media/003_building_compliant_ai_governance_frameworks.mp3" length="3450669" type="audio/mpeg" /><description>Narrated episode: 003 Building Compliant Ai Governance Frameworks</description></item><item><title>001 Navigating Australia S Ai Regulatory Framework</title><guid>001_navigating_australia_s_ai_regulatory_framework</guid><pubDate>Sun, 15 Jun 2025 03:34:59 +1000</pubDate><enclosure url="https://github.com/surly-16/js-audio-feed/raw/refs/heads/main/Governance,%20Value%20and%20Strategy/media/001_navigating_australia_s_ai_regulatory_framework.mp3" length="4447149" type="audio/mpeg" /><description>Narrated episode: 001 Navigating Australia S Ai Regulatory Framework</description></item></channel></rss>